[Music]
hello everybody we are live
uh it's nice to meet you all to see you
all on this fine sunday evening
morning wherever you are great to see
you all today we talk about
indian history and also about
geopolitics so before we start let me
take a look at who all is there
hi vinit hi vikramaditya
purveys
good to see you all great to see you all
and i would before i begin i would like
to thank all of you who have taken new
memberships
welcome to the new members thank you
very much for supporting the channel
hi arnov hi rohan vishnu abhishek neil
arnov
good to see you all good to see you all
so let's
get into it with today's questions let
me start with question number one
and question number one is by hussein
so this is a question from twitter
hussain says it would be
interesting to hear your opinion on the
battle of saragarhi
i see the film k3 was celebrated which
glorified the valor of british sepoys
who happened to be six and the tribesmen
attacking the post were pashtuns were
pashtun tribes
which were possibly living there for
centuries and their fight against the
british forces was a revolt for freedom
i believe it was a tragedy that indians
had to join forces with the british for
with the british and to kill their
fellow indians
that's a very interesting question
hussein
so yeah we have this film case 3 which
i think came up a couple of years ago
and it celebrated the valor of the
sick soldiers the 21 or 20 to six
soldiers who
defended this fortress and died in one
of the
most famous last stands in history and
you are right they were fighting for the
british for the british empire
and they were fighting against the
pashtun tribes people
of northwestern india present-day
pakistan
and western present day afghanistan and
western pakistan northwestern pakistan
so it was basically like you say a
battle between
the forces of the british empire and the
forces of those
people of the region who are fighting
for their freedom so to understand
this battle and what really happened we
have to look at the bigger context
we can't just discuss the battle and the
tactics and on what happened there
we have to look at the bigger context to
understand what really happened
and why those things happen if you look
at a very narrow slice of history a
narrow time period
then we will get a very narrow
perspective of what actually happened
if we widen our perspective and look at
a bigger
time period then we actually understand
the forces
at work and why these things happen
so it all begins so where should we
begin basically i think we should begin
a thousand years before today
approximately 1000 years ago when the uh
islamization of afghanistan took place
so we had these invasions happening from
the west
first it was the invasions of muhammad
bin qasim who was part of the was an
arab
and the later invasions were all turkic
invasion these were the invasions that
actually
uh succeeded eventually in
conquering india you first had the
various turkic
invaders you had the delhi slave dynasty
the maam looks and then you had the
mughals etc the so-called mughals who
were actually turks
so the islamization of afghanistan began
around a thousand years ago when the
gori dynasty which was a buddhist
dynasty
and probably before that there were
hindus there's no real difference
so they were the ones who got converted
to islam and they continued
ruling afghanistan but that was that
became the
that's that began the islamic era of
afghanistan now
afghanistan got converted reasonably
rapidly to islam
there were hindus and six living there
until until very recently
there's very few left now but
afghanistan has
always for thousands of years been the
northern part
of india the northernmost part of india
right the people of gandhar
it was called gandhar in vedic and
mahabharata times
and the people of afghanistan the true
people of afghanistan the pashtuns are
basically an extension of the indian
population
they are the same genetically the
infamous genetics argument right
they are basically the same ethnically
even culturally
their underlying deep down culture is
the same as that of
the rest of india of course today they
do not see themselves as indians
they are a separate nation and that's a
fact that's a fact that cannot be
denied so it's a separate country now so
it all begins with the
uh islamization of afghanistan then you
fly fast fast forward a few hundred
years you had uh
share sha suri who fought the mughals
who fought the turkic invaders which we
now call the mughals
and he basically conquered northern
india northern parts of india
he conquered delhi he used he he evicted
the mughals from delhi and
ruled over delhi for a period of five
years
uh i think it was was it i think it was
humayun who was evicted
by shasturi so sher shah suri saw
himself as an indian
as a muslim of course was but as an
indian and he saw the turks as
foreigners
right and after shasuri's death soon we
had
another indian emperor hemachandra
vikramaditya who had
mostly a pashtun army his army was
mostly afghans
more than 90 or almost 100 of his troops
were afghans so hema chandra
vikramaditya became the last hindu
emperor of delhi
even though his entire army was mostly
muslims but he was crowned the hindu
emperor in a hindu ceremony
and when he eventually lost to
the forces of akbar who was then 13
years old
right i think it happened in the year 15
50 something 15 55 56
when he lost to akbar his
head was cut off and it was taken to
kabul to terrorize the locals
to show them what was done to their king
right so until that time afghans and
indians were more they considered each
other the same people despite the
difference in religion
and they all considered the turks to be
foreigners
so indians and afghans fought together
at the time
right so that like so so that basically
uh corroborates what hussein is saying
that the
pashtun tribesmen were indians then you
had the
durrani invasion so so uh
this guy ahmad shah durrani
abdali whatever he invaded india from
afghanistan several times there were
like seven
eight invasions which took place in the
18th century
he took over parts of india he occupied
kashmir for about a century or so
right he also assisted the persian
emperor nadarsha in his invasion of
india which was a bloodbath
right and then you had the sikh empire
that began
in the at the end of the 18th century
the beginning of the
19th century and that basically pushed
the pashtuns back
push the questions back all the way to
what is now called the duran line
right so then you had about 30 40 years
of the sikh
empire under maharaja ranjit singh which
pushed the pashtuns back
by about 1830 to the present-day border
of pakistan and afghanistan
which is called the duran line and then
you had the beginning of the great game
when the british empire and the roman
and the sorry not roman russian empire
fought i mean they
vied for supremacy in the central east
in the central asian region
uh because they both because the british
wanted to defend india
which was their golden goose and the
russians wanted to take over india
so that was a great game then you had
the first
anglo afghan war which was a disastrous
defeat for the
british which was in 1838 i think then
you had the anglo-sikh wars in 1845
1848 the second anglo-sikh war was a
victory for the british
the six lost and then what happened was
you began to see these conflicts between
the british and the afghans
so you had the second anglo-afghan war
in 1878
and in 1893 i think the duran line was
demarcated
which basically cut off a great portion
of the pashtun heartland
from afghanistan and that problem still
continues today because many of these of
these pashtun regions
are today in pakistan the afghans don't
recognize the durant line as the
border right so this is the background
to what happened in 1817
1897 when this battle of saragori
happened
so the british wanted to invade
afghanistan and subdue it the afghans
the tribes people
the pashtuns wanted to fight for their
independence
so in 1897 these british
forts were there in this region the
sarakari region
it was called the thira campaign so
these forts were placed in order to
subdue the tribes people
and what happened was that the one of
these fortresses
was called salagari it was between fort
gulistan and fourth something else
it was manned by 21 or 2 6 and the
afghans were basically fighting for
their freedom
they wanted to push the british back and
the six
basically were fighting for the british
not for india they were fighting for the
british
unfortunately that's that's the sad
story of india
indians fighting indians so what hussain
is saying it is
it is right it is a tragedy that indians
fought against indians
today their pashtuns are considered to
be afghans
most of them all of them none of them
consider themselves to be indians today
but at the time they were all indians we
know that khan abu ghafar khan fought
for united india he was a pashtun
so i think i agree with hussain it was a
tragedy that
indians fought indians that is the
history of the past
almost thousand years indians fighting
indians in the name of whatever
various foreign religions foreign
occupying powers
being made to fight against each other
so that is something that
persists even today in present-day india
in modern india
indians are still fighting indians in
the name of democracy and
and freedom of expression and god knows
what else
it's still going on nothing has really
changed so
it's an interesting uh question to begin
this
episode with so good question asan thank
you for asking this
okay question number two this is by
aditya
where is the peacock throne of shah
jahan now
so what other people is referring to is
uh what happened during the
invasion of india by nadir shah nadir
shah was a persian
iranian king he invaded
india in 1739 and uh it was a very
successful invasion because the mughal
empire was in decline at the time
the marathas were on the marathas i'm
not sure there was still very much of
force yet
if i'm right but uh the mughals were in
decline
and nadir invaded india with the aim of
capturing slaves and booty and
and wealth and all that it was a very
successful invasion he was able to
capture delhi with the help of this
ahmad shah abdali or durrani
and there was a terrible bloodbath in
delhi in one day more than a hundred
thousand more than one lakh men women
children were
massacred for no reason so
and one of the things that uh so he took
away an enormous amount of booty from
india a great deal of plunder
he was he he got he became so wealthy
that he was able to abolish taxes in
persia for like two three years
after that so that's the amount of
wealth he took back he
took back lots of slaves as well indians
right
and one of the things he took back to
persia was the mayur asan which was the
throne of shah jahan it was in the shape
of peacocks and all that it had peak of
peacock motifs carved on it so this is
one of the things that was taken back it
was
made of gold it had lots of precious
jewels and diamonds and rubies and
whatnot
on it and the question is where is this
stone today
so uh this guy nadir shah was not very
popular he was assassinated by his own
generals
just a few years later like eight years
after his invasion of india
i think it was in 1747 or something like
that
and in the aftermath of the chaos
that ensu ensued after the assassination
this peacock throne was most likely
dismantled
and it was taken apart for for the
various
jewels and all the gold it had so it was
basically destroyed it was uh
melted away and all the jewels and
everything was were extracted and
well they must have found their play
their way into various
different hands today must many of them
may be in europe perhaps in various
in the hands of various collect
collectors perhaps
so we don't really know what happened
after it was destroyed
but i'm sure that the the wealth was
redis distributed
in some way so that is what happened to
the peacock throne it was
the throne of shah jahan it was
extracted from india
from taxes raised from indians and the
gold and
jewels extracted out of india that's
what shah jahan did
and then it was stolen by nadersha and
eventually that wealth became part of
the
wealth of persia
okay kensin vlog asks why
is it that many thai cultures are pretty
much the same
as the same with india so this is
something use if we observe
all across eastern asia southeastern
asia
pretty much the bedrock the cultural
bedrock of southeast asia is is
basically indian culture
it's because of nearly 3 000 years of
indian influence
in southeast asia so it all begins with
the region of kalinga which is now
called odisha
so we have these uh
merchants from kalinga who would trade
with southeast asia
with thailand with burma with all with
parts of indonesia
cambodia laos etc right
the champa kingdom was um it wasn't the
it was one of the other kingdoms which
was founded uh
by one by a merchant
from kalinga funan it was called funan
so yeah you had a great deal of
influence for almost 3 000 years
going out of india cultural contacts
trade contacts and all that so it began
with
as far as we know it began about nearly
000 years ago with the uh voyages of the
people of kalinga to southeast
asia thailand was very much part of this
sphere of influence
and this basically increased over the
centuries
later obviously as we know very well you
had the chola
uh suzerainty over most of southeast
asia
which persisted about until about a
thousand years before today
so the chola basically chola empire
incorporated
most of southeast asia all the way to
the philippines
and the cholas they propagated sanskrit
and hinduism throughout this region
the kalingan people also did the same
and that's how we have so much uh such a
deep
impact of indian culture all across
southeast asia
so this entire region was once a hindu
region they all everyone practiced
industry not because hinduism was
imposed by force
but because it was slowly slowly
absorbed and taken up by the people of
this region
right and people some people say that
the chola spread tamil in southeast asia
because you have
tamil speaking people in malaysia and
singapore that is
not correct at all tamil peking spears
speaking people of malaysia and
singapore
are as a result of the migrations
the which happened during the british
raj era
the british sent lots of indian
indentured laborers
essentially slaves to these regions to
do hard labor
and most of these people happen to be
tamils and the people of malaysia
who speak tamil and the people of
singapore who speak tamil are the
descendants of these
these migrations did not happen during
the chola era
during the chula era what was spread was
was sanskrit
and hinduism right so
thailand was very much a recipient of
this cultural exchange
thailand was pretty much a hindu kingdom
it still
is even the thailand even today is as of
today is a buddhist country officially
it's a de facto buddhist country but the
uh royal rituals the royal coronation
weddings etc are officiated by brahmins
and these are done by
uh with hindu rituals right so the
royalty still practices hinduism
in a way because see it doesn't call
this
a hindu practice or anything because
there is no real difference i have said
this time and again there is no actual
difference
between hinduism and buddhism there is
no delineating boundary
or any such thing so that is the reason
why thailand
has so much indian culture i mean if you
go to thailand it all
is indigenous thai culture it is all
hinduism or dharmic culture with
high characteristics very much so it's
very much indigenous
and yet they are more proud of the
indian heritage than us if you go to
various parts of thailand you will see
enormous statues of ganesha and normal
statues of shiva the statues of vishnu
everywhere
you see temples of vishnu throughout
bangkok uh one of the names of bangkok
is
indrapuri right and and and in
suvarnabhumi airport in bangkok you have
this great
tableau of the samudramanthan so these
are all
manifestations of thailand's ancient
hindu
heritage indian heritage and that's the
reason why
it is there because of these almost 3000
or even longer
years of contact between india and
the rest of southeast asia india has
always been a
net exporter of culture india has always
exported its culture to other places
india has absorbed culture only in the
past 1000 years
and that too under duress it was not
willing
it was not done willingly it was imposed
upon india
but indian culture has spread outwards
always
willingly india has never forcibly
imposed its culture anywhere
whether it's in japan or china or korea
or anywhere in southeast asia
so that is the reason my friend why thai
culture is pretty much
the same as indian culture if we look
underneath
the surface
movie buff asks explanation on the
recent pakistan and afghan and taliban
situation
also how taliban can be harmful to india
also the history of these taliban and
pakistan collaboration
so the current situation is that
basically uh
that the taliban has essentially taken
over afghanistan large parts of
afghanistan i would say more than eighty
percent of afghanistan
seems to be if we uh see the reports it
seems to be under
uh taliban control to some extent of the
other
the afghan government is
trying to fight back but the taliban
have captured great
very large amounts of territory i think
kandahar is seems to be under assault
from the taliban
kabul is still holding out i hope it
holds out i really fear for the safety
of the people in kabul so that is a
situation and as we know the taliban is
a creation of pakistan
so what is the background right so the
background
is that in the 1980s you afghanistan was
a very nice
modern country it was almost like a
first world country it had very good
standards of living
excellent education external
infrastructure it was almost like a
european country
men women had equal rights more or less
and so on
and then what happened was you had uh
the soviets
invaded afghanistan with with the
objective of expanding their sphere of
influence
they invaded afghanistan and then there
was a civil war so the americans
did not like this at all because the
americans want to maintain their
hegemony worldwide
and and that was the time of the cold
war so
these two superpowers were vying with
each other for influence globally
and if the soviets were to take over
afghanistan it would greatly expand
their footprint
so the americans uh
basically they partnered with pakistan
and
they trained these mujahideen these
afghan rebels they gave them cash they
gave them
training they gave them arms and
ammunition and this basically became a
guerrilla war
between the mujahideen who were
supported by the u.s and pakistan
so between the mujahideen and the
soviets and the soviets did not do a
very good job eventually in the late
1980s they had to
leave afghanistan it was a humiliating
defeat for them
so the mujahideen succeeded but
afghanistan was ravaged
it was completely ravaged and the
mujahideen were basically
they imposed this extremely regressive
world view upon afghanistan and so the
1990s was a period of great strife the
the president of ghana afghanistan the
soviet puppet uh
najibullah met a very bad end at the
hands of the of the of the taliban i
think
so the mujahideen morphed into taliban
after the soviet invasion
ended and the afghan war ended these
mujahideen were redirected into kashmir
in 1989 and the indian government did
basically nothing and that's why kashmir
basically exploded into volatility and
insurgency in the late 1980s 89 1991
that was the worst period of
kashmir insurgency it was all
done by pakistan they redirected the
afghan mujahideen and all the various
terrorists
into kashmir in india the indian
government of the time allowed this to
happen
so that is the background and then they
they created this force called the
taliban the pakistanis
they basically rebranded these
terrorists as the taliban
this all began with who basically uh
changed the education system made it
very regressive
and this gave rise to various terrorist
outfits with the aim of liberating
kashmir from india
right and this also gave birth to the
taliban
and the pakistan dream is to use
afghanistan
as basically their strategic backyard it
gives them strategic depth
they imagine in the future a great war
with india to destroy
to reclaim kashmir and destroy india and
basically
conquer india and they want to fight to
the last afghan so they want to use the
people of
afghanistan as cannon fodder in this war
and all of this is part of that so
taliban basically is
a pakistan proxy its aim is to occupy
afghanistan
afghanistan as a pakistani uh
as a vasal state of pakistan right so
that's what it is
so pakistan has basically succeeded
right now
it is in the process of succeeding
unfortunately so what happened was that
after the 9 11 bombings
9 11 terrorist incident in the united
states the americans
bombarded afghanistan they went to war
in afghanistan they evicted
the al-qaeda and the mujahideen and the
taliban etc
to some extent from afghanistan they
were in afghanistan for about 20 years
right and now they have left the country
the problem is the americans did not
ever destroy the taliban
i mean they claim that they are the
various terrorist factions and forces in
afghanistan
were responsible for the 9 11 terrorist
attack
and their mastermind was osama bin laden
well why did they not destroy the
taliban completely
why did they allow the taliban to to
have
safe sanctuary in pakistan why did they
not
sanitize the whole of afghanistan and
make sure that
that by the time they leave afghanistan
is safe and secure they did not do that
i think their their end game
was always to leave afghanistan in chaos
and their end game also seems to be to
to drag china into the afghanistan
mess because afghanistan has
traditionally been the so-called
graveyard of empires
the russians failed the british failed
before that the americans also seemed to
have failed
so the reasoning seems to be that that
china will also fail but the
the calculation is i'm my opinion wrong
because the chinese have a border
through tibet with afghanistan so the
chinese
well they have an advantage that these
other so-called empires never had
so i think the americans want the
chinese to get dragged into this and
suffer a defeat there but it may
not entirely work out the way they want
so basically the americans have used
afghanistan
and now they have thrown the afghans to
the wolves just like mohandas gandhi did
when he when he left the pashtuns
with pakistan he did he did not ensure
that
pakistan and india remain united he
agreed to partition
and all the pashtuns who had supported a
united india
were thrown to the wolves and that's
what khanna bulgar khan said to gandhi
that you have thrown us to the wolves
so once again the afghans the pashtuns
are suffering because of the actions
of an imperial power this in this case
the united united states
and there is the situation right now uh
will taliban be harmful to india well
they have taken over all the
indian infrastructure whatever india has
built there's a dam that they seem to
have taken over over there
so whatever india has invested in
afghanistan over the past 10
or so years a few billion dollars worth
of investment is all going to it looks
like it's going to fall into the hands
of taliban
and it could also possibly have some
blowback in
in the kashmir region if pakistan tries
another misadventure they are quite
cautious now after the after what india
has done to them in the past couple of
years the bala court thing the surgical
strikes so pakistan is very cautious
nowadays
so india seems to be okay but the indian
interests in afghanistan have been
sacrificed and
india is currently in no position to
exert any kind of influence
in afghanistan so that's the situation
as of today
siddhant asks why exactly has america
pulled itself out of afghanistan knowing
that china will now have free have a
free hand
to expand there what's america's end
game for the middle east let's talk
about afghanistan so like i said the
americans
kind of had this exit plan that they
would leave
eventually afghanistan at the mercy of
the taliban
and they knew that china is basically
taking over pakistan pakistan has become
a colony of china nowadays
so the keys to the taliban are in
rawalpindi which is pakistan's military
headquarters
but the keys to rawalpindi are in
beijing because rawalpindi
is basically the attack dog off of china
right so that's the game that's being
played the taliban are a proxy of
pakistan
pakistan is a proxy of china so the
taliban are essentially
a proxy of china and they have welcomed
china's chinese
involvement in afghanistan with open
arms they are saying that they will be
happy
if the chinese were to rebuild
infrastructure in afghanistan etc
what the chinese want is one they want
to expand their
sphere of influence and they want to
further encircle india
secondly they want to exploit all the
various resources that afghanistan is so
rich in
there is the mess monastery in ancient
buddhist
monastery which sits on top of an
enormous copper deposit
so the chinese want to destroy the
monastery and take out all the copper
and much more so the chinese have
various
interests in afghanistan that's why
that's why they are
slowly getting involved very cautiously
in afghanistan
there is the chinese foreign minister
wang yi
recently met with a taliban delegation
in beijing
so you can see how things are moving so
the
american plan is to ensure that china
gets
entangled in the afghanistan and
imbroglio
and they are most likely hoping that
china will also
suffer a humiliation or a disastrous
defeat
long-term defeat the way the british did
the way the russians did
and now the way the americans have also
ignominiously
left afghanistan but their calculations
could be very wrong because the chinese
actually have a land border
through tibet with afghanistan
and via pakistan also because pakistan
is more or less a chinese colony
and therefore it may not be so hard so
so easy
to dislodge the chinese from afghanistan
especially
when the taliban are welcoming the
chinese with open arms
so the short-term outlook of afghanistan
looks bleak to me unfortunately i
i fear for the safety of those in kabul
the chinese want to engulf this region
and that seems to be the reason why
america has pulled out america is a
declining power now it is very visible
america's power is waning the chinese
power is rising
and that's what we are witnessing and
india is watching
chiranjit majumdar asks tell us
something about the
hal marut and why it is stopped
so the hindustan aeronautics limited
marut
was a fighter plane was an indian
fighter jet
it was the first fighter plane that was
developed in
india it was most likely in the first
asian fighter plane which was developed
in asia
so the designer of this aircraft was
kurt
tank who was a german aeronautics
engineer
he was a he was a very renowned and and
successful engineer and designer so he
designed this
plane and it was called the marut
it was in the 1960s i think that in the
in the beginning of the 1960s that this
development took place and i think the
first
uh production aircraft was delivered to
the indian air force in the
late 1960s now this was a very good
design
for a first design for the first fight
for the first fighter aircraft countries
produced
it was a brilliant design it was very
good plane it
nevertheless had a couple of
deficiencies it's
power plant which means its engine was
not powerful enough and this was a
political problem
india was either unable or unwilling
to acquire a powerful enough jet engine
from the west and secondly it was not
able or not willing to invest the
resources in developing
a powerful indigenous jet engine and
therefore the this plane was
hampered by the fact that it used a very
underpowered engine
and that's why it was never able to
exceed mach 1 which is the supersonic
limit
and yet it was a very good plane it it
saw action military action in 1971 it
did quite well
uh it was involved in the battle of
longiwala in which pakistan suffered a
disastrous defeat
from the air there's another movie about
that called border or something
so yeah it was a good plane it was a
very good plane but
it was decommissioned in the early 1980s
and
no further development was done i mean
if you have
a version one of a plane which is quite
good you should
iterate upon it and improve it that's
how you build
better and better planes that's what
every country has done you first
build one plane which is good enough
reasonably good and then you slowly over
the years and decades improve upon it
slowly slowly slowly
you create version two version three
version four then you create different
offshoots
with two engines or maybe some other
configuration and that's how you build
your own
defense industry and you build on your
own array of fighter aircraft
in the case of india you created the the
the
marut you refused to put
a powerful enough engine in it and then
you kill the program and that was it
so this was all politics indian
politicians you know how they are
there they there were lots of
inducements from western countries
to indian politicians and various indian
regimes
to acquire military hardware
including fighter planes from the west
but if you have your own fighter planes
which you have developed indigenously
then how can you buy fighter planes from
the west
and then how can you get kickbacks and
what the various other benefits so this
is the reason why
this wonderful fighter plane project was
killed off
and that's why india still is struggling
to have uh an indigenous arms industry
of its own now we have the lcas which is
which is an excellent aircraft it needs
to be improved
upon everything needs to be improved
improved upon but the lca pages is an
excellent fighter plane
of in its class so if india had
persisted with the
h.o.l marut and improved upon it india
may today have
had a number of different fighter
aircraft which were
derived from it unfortunately india's
politicians did not
pursue india's national interest they
pursued money
and this wonderful fighter plane program
was killed off so that
is the sad story and the usual story
of of indian arms and ammunition
development so that's what happened with
the h.o.l maruti
okay this is the next question india is
working on its jet
engine called kaveri for the past 30
years what's the status of the jet
engine development in india
without jet engine india cannot be a
superpower in the aviation field
you are right without a jet engine of
its own
india cannot be a superpower or any kind
of power in the evasion field it will
always have to
acquire jet engines from other countries
so this kaveri jet engine has been in
development like you said for the past
30 or so years as of today it is still
not
successful right it's not still uh
achieved its objectives i have heard
that recently the french
the french firm snecma was
believed to have offered a transfer of
technology to
make this uh coverage engine work
as part of the offsets in the rafal deal
i don't know what's happened with it
there is no uh
there's no new news that's come out of
this project so it seems to be in the
doldrums
sometimes no news is good news sometimes
if you're making progress you should
keep quiet about it
sometimes even if you have succeeded you
should not announce it i agree i
understand that but
i don't know i mean there has been no
news
about this project it seems to be as far
as we can tell at the same level
we have we seem to have made no
breakthroughs thus far and the the truth
is that
developing jet engines is very difficult
you know jet engines the thing is india
has very good
jet i mean rocket engines right we have
a number of very successful very
reliable rocket engines
we have a number of missiles which use
solid fuel
rockets we have the the pslv and the
gslv various iterations of these
rockets which use very powerful vikas
engines and whatnot
these are liquid-fueled engines in the
case of
jet turbines it's a very different
technology
the thing is that you need to be
extremely adept at materials
science in order to build a good
reliable jet engine because the
temperatures inside the jet engine
which basically impinge upon the turbine
they are in the thousands of degrees
celsius
so you need to be able to develop very
specific materials that can
withstand such incredibly high
temperatures for a very long time
for thousands of hours right so that is
the challenge
in developing a jet engine you can
always design a jet engine that can work
you can do it on
in the computer programs and all and you
can test it out but the
material has to be able to withstand
those temperatures and that is the
challenge you have to develop these jet
engine
blades out of a single crystal of metal
so that's usually what
happens in the west that's that's how
they've succeeded in
building reliable jet engines and that's
where india has been struggling thus far
i don't know where the progress
uh has reached as as far as we know
there's been no new announcement
about any any progress in this
matter so i agree that india needs to
develop a number of jet engines for
various aircraft it cannot keep relying
on
rolls-royce engines or various other
general electric engines for
its its aircraft india needs to develop
its own jet engines the russians have
done
it the chinese seem to have almost
succeeded now
in developing their own jet engines
india needs to take this
very seriously and have its own
reliable proven jet engines in the next
five to ten years maximum
so this is something that needs to
happen it needs to be taken up on an
urgent basis
comprehensive says dude i disagree with
you and i have two reasons
first india is not the richest empire in
the world mansa musa kingdom was
so uh this is uh with reference to the
video i made about chinggis khan
why chunguskan refused to invade india
in which i said that india was the
richest country
in the history of in the known history
of humanity
so this gentleman is disagreeing he's
saying that mansa musa's kingdom was the
richest empire in the world not
india and this is a comment i have got
lots of times
this is a question many people have
asked me yesterday ranveer allahabadi
also
sent me a one of the link about this so
hi ranvir if you're watching i'm sure
you all know who he is
right so so what's the truth
so uh here here's the fact uh mansa musa
was a king of mali so where is mali
let's go to the map let me show you on
the map because we need to
the map is our best friend okay here's
the map
let's take a look at western africa
so as you can see here if you can see my
mouse pointer this is the modern day
nation of mali
so the kingdom of mali was in this
region it included mauritania ghana
uh guinea and kodiwa
etc this this entire region of western
africa
this southwestern region of ancient of
ancient africa was called
the kingdom of mali and their king was
mansa musa
now this uh region is very influential
even in the us today
what we call blues music comes from
western africa so you have many
uh musicians like tuwani diyabati and
and many other musicians so it's been a
very influential region
even in modern times this was a very
rich region
in the past uh in the first half of the
of the second millennium ce
and this kingdom of mali had very
extensive gold resources
and that's why the kingdom of mali was
very rich so mansa musa was
the king of mali in the early 14th
century okay he was the king in the
early 14th century i think
between 13 10 and 13 25 30 thereabouts
okay
and he is reputed to be the richest
individual in the history of the world
in the known history of the world so his
wealth
is estimated to be in today's dollars
to be worth about 400 billion dollars in
today's money
400 billion dollars that was his worth
in today's money so if we compare jeff
bezos has a
is worth about 177 or 180
billion dollars today elon musk is about
150 billion dollars worth
and bill gates is worth about 125
billion dollars as of
today this this month so if you compare
mansa musa he was worth about 400
billion
dollars at that time
now does that make the kingdom of mali
the richest empire in the world does it
does it really
so think about it this way you have
heard of the
great uh shri padmanabhaswami temple
in kerala one temple right now recently
it was
discovered that it contains an enormous
treasure which has been donated to this
temple
over thousands of years and the
minimum value of the treasure in this
one temple
exceeds one trillion dollars right
so there is more than two and a half
times the entire wealth of mansa musa in
one
indian temple and it's
just one temple so that is the
comparison you need to see
one individual being super rich doesn't
make his country
the richest country in the world let me
show you a different example
let's uh let me show you a different uh
let me share my screen and show you an
image
here we are okay so this is from
angus madison's book angus madison is a
very famous
i think american economist he did a
comparative
study of the gdps of the world
in in ancient history starting from as
you can see here
1 180 all the way to 2003 a.d
and what he found is that india was
consistently
the richest country in the world for the
best part of the first 1500 years
since 180 right and in my opinion he has
made certain oversimplifications
india may have and according to his
calculations india accounted for at
least a third of the world's gdp
for most of this time period in my
opinion if he had calculated correctly
and not made certain assumptions
india would have been closer to half of
the world's gdp but that's not the point
here
if we see the data here this is india
if you can see my mouse pointer and you
can see the gdp right
180 1000 ad 1580 et cetera compare
africa with it
in 180 okay mansa usa musa was in the
13th century so it's closer to
1500. so at that time india's gdp was
this here 60 500 and look at africa's
gdp the whole of africa
19383 less than one
third of india's gdp and that's the
whole of africa not just mali
and therefore despite mansa busa
being the richest human in human history
that wealth that he had was just
a drop of water in the ocean india
was historically the richest
civilization in the history of humanity
for most of history and even what the
europeans called pre-history
because i i would say that during the
harappan era of india's history
india may have accounted for two-thirds
of the entire world gdp that's how rich
india was
that's how large the civilization was
that's how prosperous it was
and it was completely fully
industrialized at that time
three thousand four thousand years
before bce
so india has always been the richest
civilization in the history of the world
despite mansa musa being the richest
individual that we know of
his wealth was just a small drop in the
ocean
in the big in the context of the big
picture right
so i hope that explains and and puts
this question to rest
right mansa musa's kingdom was rich yeah
sure but it was
nothing not nothing compared to what
india was in its entirety
now another question i would like to ask
you is where did all this wealth go
why is mali so poor today
right if mansa wasa musa was so rich and
he had so much gold and so much wealth
then why is mali so desperately poor
today
and the answer is what is the official
language of mali today what do they
speak in their official communications
they speak for say they speak french it
was french colonization that
extracted all the wealth out of mali and
that's why europe is so rich because
africa was very rich and europe
colonized africa
they divided up africa the french the
germans the dutch the
belgians the british the italians and
who else everyone
and they extracted everything of value
out of africa
and also out of india and that's how
europe became so rich and that's how
there is no gold left in mali today
all these enormous reserves of gold were
extracted out of mali
by the french and the french were not
the only ones
there were so many more abuses done to
africa by the various europeans
that's how africa is dirt poor today
that's how africa is in such
abject poverty and misery despite
it having had brilliant beautiful
culture and beautiful civilizations
throughout throughout its history so
that is what colonization does
and that's how africa ended up where it
is today
right so i hope this answers your
question
aditya asks we keep hearing countries
uniting against terrorism
and we also know the places from where
they operate yes we do
then why does terrorism still exist why
haven't we finished it off yet
well who is we who's we
we in india want to finish off terrorism
but our government doesn't have the
wherewithal to do it it doesn't build
its influence
it's sphere of influence beyond our
borders we still are dealing with
problems within our borders
and we are completely unable to
influence anything that happens beyond
our borders
afghanistan is a strong stone's throw
away from us we have invested billions
of dollars in afghanistan
and we have now allowed all of that
investment to fall into the hands
of the taliban that's one thing so we if
you're talking about india
india is not doing anything to expand
its sphere of influence
right india is not building hard power
india keeps harping on about soft power
so terrorism terrorism
why does terrorism still exist well
terrorism still exists because it is
useful
there are many powers in the world that
want to
well do things that don't really
fall within the norms of
acceptable behavior internationally and
therefore they use proxies
the taliban uses sorry the pakistanis
have are well known to have used proxies
terrorist proxies in india
in kashmir in other parts of india in
mumbai attacks and other attacks
throughout
throughout the country and also in
afghanistan in the form of the taliban
the americans used the mujahideen
against the soviets
in afghanistan the mujahideen gave rise
to osama bin laden who then attacked the
u.s
right then you have the middle east you
have this various terrorist proxies over
there also you have the abu nidal gang
in the 1980s that no one remembers today
and then
various other terrorist organizations
you have
terrorist organizations in somalia et
cetera everywhere
so these are all proxies of larger
powers
that want to ensure that their hegemony
continues
worldwide and they use
terrorists and terrorist outfits as
disposable
means of expanding or maintaining
their power and their hegemony in
various regions
one of the regions that's always in
conflict is the middle east
the other one is uh is the indian
subcontinent the western part pakistan
afghanistan all that
so these terrorist outfits and this
phenomenon of terrorism is useful
for big powers because it enables them
to
achieve certain foreign policy
objectives and certain
interests of their certain agendas of
theirs without actually
being seen to be involved in these
matters
and that's why terrorism is so useful
that's why
you have outfits like isis al-qaeda
taliban various various terrorist
outfits that pakistan
sends into kashmir etc so these are all
extremely useful
and that's why many large powers
turn a blind eye to their operation and
actually
help them out so that's what's happening
okay this is by vicky why didn't
china lose the mandate of heaven why
didn't
didn't the chinese communist party lose
the mandate of heaven when defeated by
the vietnamese
so the chinese uh invaded vietnam
in the late 1970s i think 1979 was it
they invaded vietnam and they suffered a
disastrous defeat at the hand of the
hands of the vietnamese
army and it was a disaster yes
it was a military disaster it was it was
a debacle
so i had said in one of my previous
episodes that there is
a concept called the mandate of heaven
so historically chinese emperors were
seen
seen to have the mandate of heaven when
they were able to rule the country
with a strong firm hand
and when they lost uh
a military engagement or a military
campaign that's that's when they were
said to have lost the mandate of heaven
and that's when the people rebelled
against them and that's when
dynasties would fall and eventually new
dynasties would emerge
so basically you would lose the mandate
of heaven
if you were to have a terrible military
defeat
and i extended this concept to apply to
the chinese communist party
i said that the chinese communist party
is nothing but a new imperial dynasty
and the only way they will go out of
power is if they
experience a catastrophic military
defeat somewhere
in which case they will be seen to have
lost legitimacy and the mandate of
heaven
in the eyes of the chinese people and
then that's when you would have a
rebellion
whether it's internal to the to the ccp
or external to it within china
so now this is a good question it's a
brilliant question why didn't the ccp
the chinese communist party
lose this mandate of heaven when
defeated by the vietnamese
it's because they were able see in 1978
79 china was a
closed society it was very much like
what north korea is today
there was no influence of the external
world into china there was no internet
there was no bbc there was no cnn there
was nothing
the only news media whatever the chinese
people would be
would consume was all official chinese
communist party
news and propaganda that's all so what
happened in vietnam
did not ever reach the eyes and ears of
the chinese
population because all news was strictly
controlled
so i would expect that this military
defeat
was twisted into a military victory for
the chinese
population and they must have been told
that we taught the vietnamese a great
lesson
and we killed so many of the soldiers
and we then came back after teaching
them the lesson so that's the kind of
spin that must have been given
to this entire debacle by the chinese
communist party
and that's how they were not seen to
have lost the mandate of heaven
if something like that were to happen
today in today's age of the internet
in the age of the um what do you call it
vpns so the chinese people are able to
circumvent the great firewall using vpns
virtual private networks so it's
impossible today
for such a debacle to remain secret and
if such a debacle were to happen today
then the chinese people would come to
know about it then dissatisfaction would
rise
exponentially and there would be a
rebellion may be within the chinese
communist party itself
a coup of thoughts or there could be
rebellions
in chinese territory as well so that's
the thing they were able to
sanitize the the the version of what
happened and they were able to
project it as a chinese victory to the
chinese people and that's why
there was no dissatisfaction or
rebellion anywhere
so that's how it happened
siddhant asks america wants to protect
its hegemony china wants infinite
expansion
india wants to become a superpower
what's russia's endgame
where does it ultimately what does it
ultimately aspire other than counter
balancing
now china and now america and in the
future china
well i disagree that india wants to
become a superpower india's people
want india to become a superpower
india's government is doing nothing in
the direction because to become a
superpower
you need to exponentially increase your
hard power and your power projection
capabilities
what's india doing about it nothing
right
you can't become a superpower through
slogans
look at the united states in the past
why was it the superpower
because it was able to project power
globally at a moment's notice
why was russia's superpower the ussr
because it was also able to project
project power globally
at a moment's notice and it was very
much it had a very strong presence
globally
diplomatic presence economic presence
and military presence globally
warships submarines aircraft carriers a
blue water navy
so does india have any of that is india
even trying to develop that
no therefore india's government doesn't
seem to aspire
towards india becoming a superpower
india's people do want it
but india's people are their aspirations
are falling on deaf ears
now about russia what is russia's end
game
so russia's endgame is mr vladimir
putin's in-game because
he is the de facto emperor or tsar of
russia
so vladimir putin is basically
uh trying to expand russia's sphere of
influence
whether it is in the donbass region
whether it is in ukraine whether it's in
the crimea
whether it's in central asia he sees all
of this
this uh these territories as russia's
native sphere of influence russia's
natural
sphere of influence russia's historical
sphere
of influence so basically mr putin is
like a tsar he has imperial ambitions
he's basically he is the emperor
of russia he calls he is called the
president but that's what he actually is
now the americans have encircled russia
through western europe etc
from afghanistan as well they try to do
that right
and that is what russia has tried to
counter balance and they have
created a de facto alliance with china a
quasi alliance with china
to counter balance the americans now
russia is very much aware
that the chinese are also a long-term
threat to it the chinese are an
expansionist power
the chinese will be content with nothing
except global domination
so that will eventually conflict with
russia's
self-interests so the long-term future
between russia and china is that of
conflict that is
given it's guaranteed even today russia
has pointed ballistic nuclear missiles
at china in various places right
so the problem with russia is that
it doesn't seem to have a proper
succession plan
the chinese communist party has a very
clear plan of succession
they will have political continuity the
next president will be somebody from the
chinese communist party somebody who is
appointed by the politburo by the
national executive or whoever it is
and the overall long-term objectives of
the chinese communist party will
remain unchanged no matter who becomes
the next
president in the case of russia there is
no such
body like the chinese communist party in
russia it's just a one-man game
it's vladimir putin so the question is
one day mr putin will have to step down
either when he is very old or whatever
whatever the circumstances are one day
a new person will come in his place
so will that person continue
with the same policies and plans and
will that person have the same
objectives
long-term national objectives as mr
putin so is there a proper succession
plan
the succession plan is what ensures
continuity of
a civilization a kingdom an empire
country whatever
why did the mongol empire break up
because the succession
was problematic why does any empire
break up
because of problems in the succession in
the chinese
in the case of china they have a good
succession plan
it's a very stable system in the case of
russia we still don't know
so that is the main question that's the
big question
will russia have political stability and
continuity
in the next 10 20 years when mr putin
will definitely be much older
will he be able to continue in power or
will he delegate his power and authority
to somebody else
or will it be taken from him somehow
this is the big question in russia so
that
is a big unknown right now and that is
also what the chinese are waiting for
because they are the chinese have a 100
year plan they don't plan for the next
five years the way we do in india
every five years we have new policies
and new plans there is no continuity
so that is the question as of today we
don't know the end game
i think russia doesn't have any
expansionist hegemonic ambitions
it wants to be a major power it wants to
remain a major
power and it wants that to continue it
doesn't seek
global hegemony the way the americans
seek or the chinese seek
but will it be allowed to
continue playing that role is the big
question
mr putin is very strong he's a very
strong man right we know his policies
are very good very
and uh and very clear he's got clarity
of thought he's got clarity of action
and uh and plans and strategy and all
that but after him what happens that is
the main question
and that is a big big unknown as of
today
iguala asks why did napoleon fail in
egypt
napoleon failed in egypt because he was
over ambitious and he tried to bite off
too
much much more than he could chew so
egypt was very far away from
from france right we know should we
shall we look at the map
okay let's look at the map give me a
minute i'll show you
just a minute
okay here's the map so let us go over
here so napoleon was the emperor of
france
oh this is france here and egypt is all
the way here
so as you can see it is several thousand
kilometers away from
from france so napoleon tried to invade
and conquer france his objective was to
create a base for france over here in
order to cut
off the british uh the british
route to india and eventually he wanted
to
become he wanted to take over india as
well so he was very ambitious
but the problem is that the british had
excellent
logistical lines lines of communication
lines of
transportation and lots of arrangements
to transport
goods man materials throughout this
region they had lots of military bases
there lots of
vasal states and all that france did not
have anything like that
and therefore they were overstretched
and because he was so far from his home
base
and he did not have a proper system for
getting
getting uh supplies getting
reinforcements of troops and
other things that's why eventually he
failed in his invasion of egypt
and he he lost a great part of his army
and he had to basically come back to
france
quietly and secretly so that's what
happened he
he he was over ambitious
and he tried to bite off much more than
he could chew
he what he should have done was to
slowly
steadily and patiently build his network
in this region network of supply lines
network of transportation network of of
allies
and vasal states and then he could have
done it but he was too ambitious he was
very young
and that's what eventually led to his
defeat his ultimate defeat in the battle
of waterloo
because he was very impatient so that's
the reason
why napoleon lost in egypt
siddhant asks how did nehru become so
prominent in the congress
that he became the pm despite him being
so incompetent meek suffering from
inferiority complex all his life etc
well to understand why somebody like
shri and the jawal nehru succeeded in
the congress party we have to understand
what the congress party really was
the congress party was created in the in
the 19th century
by alan hume the founder of the congress
party
was alan hume an englishman he was
british
and the aim the only aim the only
objective
of the congress party was to create a
proper
uh civilized british
mediated british overseen freedom
struggle for india
so a fake freedom struggle for for india
and that would take the shape that the
british desired it to take
basically it would be a non-violent
freedom struggle
there would be no violence so then you
could categorize all
violent freedom struggles all violent
manifestations
of india's freedom aspirations as
terrorism
so you see even that today in india's
history textbooks if you go to any
uh university textbook of history they
will portray
people like bhagat singh etc as
terrorists or extremists
so so the objective of the congress
party was to create
a fake freedom struggle right a freedom
struggle that
was led by people who were british
educated
who were anglophones who were
anglophiles and whose first allegiance
was to the crown of england
of great britain so that was the
objective the plan the agenda of the
congress party which was created by an
englishman
and if you see the history of the
congress party all of its major leaders
were all educated in england they all
spoke english as their first language
they all loved england they all owed
their allegiance to the crown
and they espoused a very gentle respect
respectful
obedient freedom struggle no violence
petitioning the government writing
letters doing non-violence
hunger strikes and things like that
and therefore the leaders and and when
somebody like
subhash chandra bose ascended to the
leadership of the congress party
it was an accident and he was very
quickly
overthrown in a coup by mohandas gandhi
gandhi engineered a political coup
within within the congress party
which led to the expulsion of subhash
chandra bose
out of the party right so the objective
of the
of the congress party was to shepherd
india's freedom struggle
in a way that suited the british so that
the british could continue on in india
as long as they wanted to and then they
could have a proper exit strategy from
india which was the partition and
destruction of india
so that was the only agenda and
objective of the
indian national congress and the exit
plan was to partition india and
install a puppet prime minister or a
prime minister of their choice
in india so essentially it was a
transfer of power
from foreign crooks to indian crooks
and they wanted somebody who was very
much indebted to them
so basically uh when the
partition happened india became a
dominion status country
then there was this internal election in
the congress party in which
sardar patel won almost all the votes it
was i think unanimous
and yet gandhi mr gandhi mohandas gandhi
armed twisted the
congress party into into basically
accepting
nehru undemocratically as the prime
minister of india
so it was not a democratic process it
was an undemocratic process
mr gandhi was basically furthering the
agenda of the british
in installing this this great person sri
naruji as
the prime minister of india so nehru did
not
did not fight an election until the
1950s i think the first
indian election parliamentary election
was in 1951
i think so 47 was merely a transfer of
power from
the british to a bunch of people the
british chose that's what it was
and that's why mr nero despite his
wonderful uh
characteristics was able to become the
prime minister of india
he was selected by the british
satwik asks why should we spend so much
money in space exploration etc when we
have so much
poverty and other problems to deal with
which requires a lot of money
why can't we spend that money in some
crisis like the current situation to
help the needy
it's a good question this is a question
that lots of people ask it's a question
that lots of foreign
uh journalists write about you have
poverty in india why do you have a space
program
why can't you use that money for
something really useful
let me tell you something today most
people in india
admire china for the accomplishments
they have been able to achieve
the chinese space program began in the
1960s and 70s with transfer of
technology
from russia so when the chinese space
program started the long march
rockets and missiles and all that
china's
more than almost almost 90 percent of
china's population was below the poverty
line
and yet they invested in the space
program and see where it is today
and see what china has been able to
achieve today if they had not invested
in their space program
in the 1960s and 70s china would not be
a near superpower today
look at india india invested in israel
in the 1960s 70s etc
today india has an oakish space program
india is able to launch its own
satellites
india is completely independent in the
space in the field of space
india doesn't need anyone's help had
india not invested in the space program
we would have had to buy satellite
bandwidth from the west at in
incredible prices all our communications
would have been monitored by the west
and other powers so we would not
have had the level of technological
and communications independence that we
have today
so despite india being a poor country
india invested in the space program and
it was
a good step it was the right thing to do
we have to solve these problems
in parallel not in sequence otherwise we
will take a
couple of centuries to reach where we
want to reach
today india is rich enough to solve all
its problems india has enough money to
solve all the problems
the problems are created created
artificially they are
these problems are persisting because of
various internal problems that india has
mostly it's politics politicians want
india to be
india to be fighting each if the people
of india
fight each other all the time because
these fights and these divisions
cause uh
these fights and divisions basically
gain them votes
and that's why that is the problem with
india's system india's so-called
democratic system
it basically pits various parts of india
against each other
so the main so the main so the issue is
that
india needs to keep investing in science
and technology while
solving its other problems in parallel
india has the resources
and the funding and the money and
everything it needs
to eliminate poverty today to make india
a better place today
it just needs the right leadership i
think we have reasonably good leadership
today
we need better leadership we always need
better leadership no matter who it is
so that's why india needs to keep
developing
and investing in its space program it is
very important we do that
harshit says as china's latest mass
project was completely successful what
challenges does it bring to isro
as our space program is delayed because
of the chinese virus yes
our program is completely stopped right
now because of the chinese virus
whereas the american space program is
continuing spacex is continuing to
launch the
launch rockets the chinese are launching
rockets every month
and so much is happening but india's
space program
is currently on hold because of the
chinese virus which is very strange
progress should never stop no matter
what happens so i am disappointed with
the fact that india's
space program is currently currently
paused
now you are right the chinese mars
project has been successful they have
been able to
land a rover on mars
if we if we believe what they are saying
they have released some video of that
etc
so chinese have not reached mars by
accident
they have been planning it for decades
they have been
uh improving the technology step by step
by step
they first targeted the moon they
reached the moon they
sent spacecraft in orbit around the moon
then they sent
a lander on the moon then they sent a
rover on the moon then they sent a
lander and rover on the far side of the
moon
then they sent a sample return mission
which has succeeded so
every new mission is a new
improvement on the technology and
because of this
iterative improvement that they have
been doing in technology
that's why now they are good enough to
send a lander and roar
to mars so that's how you progress you
do it step by step it has to be a long
term plan
does isro have a plan isro scientists
are second
to none in the world they are as good as
any scientist in china or any scientist
in nasa
or spacex we have the best scientists in
the world
my question is does the political
leadership have a vision for india
in the space race do they want india to
be a space superpower or not
or is it all about just uh launching a
few satellites for a foreign country and
getting some money out of it and is that
all
are we a taxi service is that all isro
is
or are we actually ambitious enough to
think to to
want to have a base on the moon and the
base on mars someday
and do we have a time frame on that
because a plan
is just a dream unless there is a time
frame on that and a proper step by step
approach to it
so that's what india needs india has the
potential to be on mars in the next 20
years
but it's all about the leadership it's
all about the political leadership
whether it has the ambition
and the vision to make india a space
superpower
so i hope there is something like that
in the works but as of now we see
nothing
no sign of that which is disappointing
okay question by harshit
so harshit says china has announced its
400 billion dollar investment program
in iran how challenging is it going to
be for india to consolidate its
relationship with iran
as the chabahar project is delayed
the java heart project isn't delayed
it's over
okay the chinese are investing 400
billion dollars reportedly in iran
over the next 20 30 years so what is a
few million dollars from india compared
to that
why would the iranians have any interest
anymore
in the indian project in chabahar
the chinese can take off ever take care
of everything the chabahar project
is over no matter what the indian
government says no matter what
signals they should they they and noises
they make
this project is over the only objective
of the chavah project was to connect
india to afghanistan via
now that the afghanistan now now that
afghanistan has fallen
to a great extent to the taliban into
pakistan what's the point
of having this trade route to
afghanistan
whom are you going to trade with the
taliban
so as of today the chinese have made
great inroads into afghanistan
they have allied with the iranians
the iranians have thrown everything into
the chinese camp
because the americans have been uh
squeezing them with these terrible
sanctions for decades
so now that the iranians are going to
get a great deal of relief from the
chinese because of this investment
but of course the chinese will extract
their pound of flesh
so from the perspective of india we can
forget about chabahar
until and unless we can reopen
our land access with afghanistan nothing
is going to progress
so that is the situation as of today
even hariman says the balochis are much
more useful to india as a point of
leverage with iran and pakistan
a credible point of pain that india can
bring if they don't cooperate with
india's strategic interests
as soon as they achieve statehood what
utility does balochistan offer
india very little and once you follow
through with that now your
relationship with iran is in the gutter
listen india has never had a great
relationship with iran
i have shown this i've spoken about this
in a previous episode as well
that iran has always supported pakistan
as compared to india and iran has never
been a reliable
trustworthy ally of india or even
a fair weather friend the only
relationship india and iran have
is that of trade in oil and this
proposed project in chabahar
now that the chinese investment has come
into iran all of that is over
and the u.s has already squeezed india
into into
so india has stopped buying oil more or
less from iran
so there is no real relationship left
with iran and india and iran has
historically been antagonistic towards
india
iran has its own imperial ambitions
and balochistan is a point of contention
because half
almost half of balochistan is currently
occupied by iran
so yes you're right that if india
follows through with
with helping balochistan gain
independence
its relationship with iran will be in
the qatar but it's already in the gutter
india has nothing to gain vis-a-vis iran
iran is no friend of
india right and what do we gain by
uh by bringing by allowing
the balochi people to gain independence
well we break pakistan up
pakistan is an artificial country it's a
temporary country it is india's
unfinished business
it is indian territory that has been
given away without consulting the people
of india
so it is all unfinished business
by ensuring that balochistan gains
independence you are
disintegrating pakistan and that is
that should be part of india's long-term
objective in the next 20 years
only with only when pakistan will cease
to exist in the form that exists it
exists today
only then will india have better
relationships
with the people to its west
right only then will india have peace in
the western border
and then india will be able to
concentrate elsewhere
so india needs to ensure that pakistan
is balkanized peacefully
no conflict no violence no killings
nothing peacefully
in the next 10 to 20 years this needs to
happen
because pakistan is an affront to
humanity what they're doing in
afghanistan is is monstrous it's
barbaric
they are not a force of good in the
world
they are a terrorist state they are an
army that has a country
it's not a country that has an army it
is a terrorist
state it needs to be broken up so it is
in india's
interest to break up pakistan and
to give balochistan its freedom
pink line cabs asks how should india
tackle the damning of
important rivers by china in tibet okay
so first of all
the major river that china is damning in
tibet is the brahmaputra the great river
brahmaputra
now what indians don't know is that
more than 80 percent of the water of the
brahmaputra
flows into the brahmaputra from
arunachal pradesh and assam
very little of it comes from tibet so
even if the chinese were to dam
up the river in tibet it won't really
affect
the flow of the brahmaputra very much
because more than 80
of this river of this water comes in
through arunachal pradesh and tibet from
various tributaries from rainfall and
all that
so that is number one secondly it is
still kind of an act of war if china
would
were to stop india from accessing the
waters of these of these rivers which
have been flowing into india
for thousands of years it would be
tantamount to a declaration of war
in in some sorts in a way
so the only long-term solution to this
problem is
for india to engineer freedom for tibet
in the next
10 20 30 years if india is able to
engineer freedom for tribes if india is
able to make tibet free from chinese
occupation
then for the first time in 60 70 years
india will have peace
on the northern border so that has to be
india's
long-term geopolitical objective as of
today india is not strong enough to
achieve this
so india needs to start investing
properly
in its hard power and other forms of
power and only then
will able will india be able to achieve
this objective
so the only solution is freedom for
tibet
dave sharma asks as we see china's
foreign policy is
spineless yet very effective as they
like they adapted to afghanistan's
current status
and met with the taliban do you feel
that india should also
move on this spineless policy path if
not permanent then for some time
i'm not sure what you mean by spineless
i think china's policy has a very strong
spine
china is very clear about its long-term
objectives about its long-term agenda
and it pursues them these objectives
relentlessly with great vigor
so i would not characterize china's
foreign policy as pineless i would
characterize it as
being very realistic very pragmatic
it's called real politic it has nothing
to do with
emotions or ethics or principles or
values the only
objective is the long-term national
interest of china
and that's what they're doing i think
india should take a few leaves out of
china's book
india stop india should stop talking
about
right and wrong good and bad just look
at india's long-term national interest
and pursue that
so the chinese are doing whatever it
takes for them to achieve their
geopolitical
objectives in asia they are expanding
their footprint into afghanistan
into pakistan into iran as well they are
expanding their footprint their
geopolitical footprint
so this is not a spineless move it's a
very realistic
hard power move and that's something
india should
learn from and should emulate if it
has any geopolitical
ambitions
divakar asks why hindu gods and kings
married more than one woman
so let's talk about the kings yes most
indian kings
in throughout indian history married
more than one woman
they had several wives lord rama did not
do that he had only one wife as we know
but many indian kings had multiple wives
this is because there is absolutely
nothing in the dharmic scriptures
in hinduism in buddhism jainism etc
sikhism are also against having multiple
spouses there is nothing in any
in any portion of india's culture that
says a man cannot have multiple wives
and there is nothing in the dharmic
scriptures
that says a woman cannot help have more
than one husband
so both polygamy and polyandry are
acceptable in indian culture and we have
seen
we can see examples of both in india's
history
and that's why indian kings and even
regular people would sometimes have more
than one wife
right so this entire notion that we have
today that polygamy is evil
this is a western notion in indian
culture there is no concept of
of monogamy there is no concept of
divorce as well
so we have been completely alienated
from indian culture i am not trying to
advocate polygamy or polyandry or
anything
i am just telling you as a student of
history
what the facts are there is nothing in
india's culture that
goes that that says polygamy or
polyandry
are are bad or unethical
or evil or anything like that it's your
choice if you want to
be monogamous have only one wife good
for you but if if you
if some king wants to wanted to have
multiple wives he he very much
was within his rights to do that and if
a woman wanted to have more than one
husband even that was acceptable in the
past
so today's laws constitution morality
are
all based in western morality and
we are completely deracinated we are cut
off from our culture
and that's why we we now feel that these
things are evil there's nothing evil or
right or wrong about this
it's a matter of personal choice if
somebody has multiple wives and he
treats them well i don't see anything
wrong with that
hinduism never saw anything wrong with
that dharma never saw anything wrong
with that
and the same goes for one woman having
multiple husbands so it's all about
seeing history and seeing the past
through the proper lens
right
priyarai asks as i have read during
alexander's invasion we were under the
nanda
dynasty while chandragupta was planning
to dethrone the nanda
so yeah that's a point of confusion
that's a point that
is not very clear right now we know that
uh
we know that when seleucus niketa okay
so alexander invaded india
uh somewhere in the third or fourth
century bce
and about 17 years later seleucus
nicator also tried to invade india
so when seleucus nicator who was
alexander's general tried to invade
india at the time we know for sure
that chandragupta maurya was the emperor
of india he was a very powerful emperor
he had an enormous empire now the
question
is that when alexander invaded india who
was the emperor of india
was it the nanda of the nanda dynasty or
was it chandragupta
so most historians say that it was the
nanda of the nanda dynasty
now the question is that if chandragupta
defeated
usurped the throne from him and became
the emperor of india
it would take a lot of time for him to
consolidate his power throughout the
country
especially in an era when there was no
telecommunications
right so it would take 10 20 30 years
for that to happen
but when seleucus nicaragua came to
india
as an invader just 17 years after
alexander's death
he found that there was this enormous
empire in india under one
emperor chandragupta maurya so was that
enough time
for a new emperor to take over the
country
defeat all opposition
and unify the country again was there
enough time for that and that's why this
question always keeps arising
was it chandragupta maurya or was it who
was the emperor of india
during alexander's invasion of india
that is a big question so the historical
consensus among historians
is that it was the nanda who was the
emperor during alex
alexander's time and yet there are
doubts there are still
legitimate questions which have not been
resolved yet
so as of today the consensus is it was
the nanda but we cannot be 100
sure as of today
arun says whoa whoa i watched you and
ranveer alaba they are discussing that
no
invasion happened and it's us who went
outward and we took our genes outside
but now you're saying there is
indo-greek chandragupta maurya thing
this means there's some aryan thing that
is inadvertently brought in
that means we have some aryan blood in
us not in south
but a bit in the north so what's so
so what arun is saying is that because
there was this greek invasion
there was this greek uh in indo-greek
dynasties in
in the north west of india and because
chandragupta married a greek lady
that's why there is some aryan component
in our genes
so the assumption that arun my friend is
making here is that the greeks are
audience
arun is assuming that the greeks are
audience and because there is some greek
component in our genetics in some of us
in india
little bit like half a percent or
something that's why there is aryan
invasion and there is aryan genes in us
so the assumption assumption that that
arun is making
is that greeks are aryans
now who says the greeks for aryans what
is the definition
of this term aryans
that's my question who are the audience
so the thing is this
if any ethnicity in the world
is to be given the name aryan it is the
people of the indian subcontinent and
the people of iran
only those people can be considered to
be aryan
because it is from this region that the
term arya
emerged it is an ancient sanskrit term
it was an ancient persian term as well
persian is a descendant of sanskrit
the old persian language during the time
of the haksha manish dynasty the
achaemenid dynasty
was a descendant of vedic sanskrit
and the term arya was used by them as an
ethnic term by the persians
and india in the old days was called
arya which means the abode of the aryan
people of the arya people means the
noble people
which means that all indians were arya
according to this definition
north india south india east west all of
them right
so if any people if any people are to be
called audience it is the indians and
the iranians
by indians i mean the entire
subcontinent from afghanistan to sri
lanka
bangladesh nepal all of that and let me
show
let me share an interesting thing with
you
just give me a minute there is this this
letter by the writer j.r.r tolkien
so in 1938
uh the germans wanted to publish j.r.r
tolkien's great novel
the lord of the rings in german in the
german language
but they wanted to know whether this guy
tolkien was a pure
aryan according to their definition
according to the german definition
so the german definition the nazi
definition of aryan was european white
skin blonde haired right
so they wrote to jiara tolkien asking
him whether he had aryan ancestry
or whether he had some jewish ancestry
or not so this
is the response of j.r.r tolkien
to the germans he wrote that i am not of
aryan extraction that is indo-iranian
as far as i am aware none of my
ancestors
spoke hindustani persian gypsy or
any related dialects so j.r.r tolkien
who was a linguist too was very clear
about
who are the aryan people the aryan
people
are the people of india and iran and
nobody else
so to to assume that greek blood is
aryan blood is
is inconsistent with
the facts right so yes
many of us in india would have some
fractional greek ancestry
especially those of us who live in
western india it's very much possible
but even the greeks the indo-greeks they
spoke sanskrit
they were hindus or buddhists and they
consider themselves to be indians
it's just the modern indian historians
who consider themselves to be who
consider these people to be greeks
they were culturally indian the indo
greeks like menander milinda
and various other kings were culturally
indian and culture is what matters not
dna
all right okay i hope this answers the
question
joseph hussman asks will indians
tolerate if there is a one-party system
that looks after the national interest
and the well-being of the entire nations
as indians are too sensitive about
democracy which means colonized
democracy
you know what indians tolerate
everything look at the history of the
past 1000 years
they have tolerated anything they have
survived and today we are tolerating
this fake secularism which is
the hindu phobic state our constitution
is hindu foreign our laws are hindu
phobic
our government policies are hindu phobic
our temples are under siege our temples
wealth is stolen by the government
and used for non-religious purposes and
what not
so indians tolerate everything indians
tolerate everything
indians are like sheep today
unfortunately right
so if there is a one party system that
looks after the national interest
indians will tolerate that too
indians don't worship democracy indians
worship nothing they just want to be
left alone
and live their life in peace that's the
average indian person
that's the average indian citizen man
woman child they just want to live in
peace
and pursue their own life and do
whatever they can
it doesn't matter what there's a system
on top
so i am sure that indians would very
much tolerate a one-party system
that looks after the national interest
and the well-being of the entire nation
the media will rebel against that but
the media is an agent of
outside forces the media is an agent of
the so-called
so-called international community do you
know what the international community is
let me show you the international
community this
this is the international community
so when we use the term international
community doesn't like this it means
these countries only
the rest of the world doesn't apply
so when the media talks about the and
the in the perceptions
of the international community the in
the international community will never
accept this
it means that these few countries will
not accept it
the new york times has this world view
the new york post the guardian
the ndtv the quint the squint the print
whatever
they all espouse this worldview they are
agents of this
so-called international community the
real international community
is the entire world which are
marginalized
so it doesn't matter the media will
complain
ignore them but the indian public the
indian people will
definitely tolerate a one-party system
for sure
they have tolerated everything else they
have tolerated much worse
in the past thousand years a one-party
system that looks after the national
interest will be a great
change for the better so yeah
indians will tolerate it for sure
not aditya asks i would like to ask if
you have any insights on how to
kickstart the indic renaissance
how will it transform our society
so to see what how do you bring about
renaissance a renaissance is a flowering
of culture
it is a revival and rejuvenation of
culture
and since you're talking about indeed
renaissance you mean india's indigenous
culture not various
foreign cultures that are now present
within india you're talking about
india's indigenous culture as
it should be so what are the conditions
that
that give rise to a renaissance the
conditions that give rise to a
renaissance are
prosperity economic prosperity and
geopolitical security these are the
conditions
that give rise to renaissance so the
people need to have
very high living standards which means
that they don't need to
slave in day in and day out 12 hours a
day just to put food on the table
the per capita gdp should be very high
that should that will ensure that people
have access to leisure activities
and it is these leisure activities that
lead to a flowering of the culture
and they all of this can never happen if
the country's borders are not secure
so for a renaissance to happen india
needs to become a very far powerful
country india needs to become
a regional power or a superpower
so that is what will kick-start an
indian renaissance and also
the living standards need to improve
which means india's economy needs to see
double-digit growth for the next 20-30
years
that is what will kick start an indic
renaissance it all starts with hard
power
military power and economic power and
all the
hindu phobic policies and the hindu
phobic constitution and laws
need to be thrown out and something
indigenous needs to be put in its place
so that is what would kick start an
indic
renaissance all right that brings me to
the end of all these questions let me
see what you are
talking about live
do you have any questions i'll take a
few live questions
saurov asks there were there any great
universities in southern and indian
eastern territories of india like
nalanda and tarchashila
or where they all concentrated only in
the north india's universities were
everywhere
wherever you had a great temple you had
a great
uh center of learning uh nalanda itself
is in the east right
it's in the east of india it's in
present-day bihar if i'm not mistaken
nalanda was in the east of india telhara
was in the east of india
you had universities all across india
everywhere north south east west
you had universities outside the
present-day geographical location of
india you had universities throughout
greater india
throughout central asia throughout the
so-called xinjiang region of china
which was a great center of learning by
the way you had universities in tibet
your university is in present-day
indonesia in cambodia
angkor wat is a great temple complex it
was also an educational complex
so you had this flowering of education
throughout
greater india and all of that has been
wiped out today
which is terrible so that's the answer
to your question they were everywhere
not just in the north
all right let me see some more questions
yashash asks can we leverage taiwan
militarily and diplomatically the same
way china uses pok against india
china uses pok against india because
it's able to project military power
all the way in this region you actually
have chinese soldiers in pakistan
occupied kashmir and china has a direct
land connection
with pakistan occupied kashmir via
the parts of kashmir that have been
seeded do it
and via tibet so the chinese have
infrastructure
and supply routes and supply chains and
military infrastructure all the way into
pok
that's why they are able to leverage it
against us now do we have
any power projection capabilities in the
south china sea
we have none and therefore we cannot
leverage taiwan militarily
in that manner in the way the chinese
use pok
diplomatically india doesn't even
leverage it doesn't even
recognize taiwan as a country and
therefore we are not able to leverage
it diplomatically as well india has one
of the smallest diplomatic core
in the world india has a total of 1700
diplomats which is less than the number
of diplomats singapore has
so these are the deficiencies and
drawbacks in the indian system
these are all deliberate these are all
intentional
india doesn't want to rise as a big
power and it is something the government
of india can change
tomorrow if it wishes
so that's where we are
nathan says why do the people of kashgar
not
look like us perhaps you say it is part
of india uttarkashi listen
central asia xinjiang was part of india
was today it is not part of india the
demographics have changed
you had the turkic invasions which
destroyed
indian culture throughout this region
the uh
native people of xinjiang today either
are the uyghurs
who are you could say ethnically half
indian half turkic
right so that's why they don't look like
us because the turks invaded the region
they killed all the men and took all the
women
and that's how the people of kashgar
don't look like us look like us today
do you understand this is what happens
this is what happened in history
so it was all part of greater india in
the past it is no longer part of india
today
even the ethnicity has changed
pariksit asks you may find this question
very silly no sir no question is silly
ask me anything you like
i will take your questions if i can find
them
can you explain the meanings of the
terms b c e c e
a d and how the ancient times are
measured using these terms
bce means before the christian era
ce means the christian era a.d means
anna domini means the ear of our lord
these are all christian terms nowadays
they have been secularized by saying
by by rephrasing them as before the
common era
and common era but it all begins with
the year in which
jesus christ is supposed to have been
born
so this is a eurocentric worldview and
they consider everything that happened
before
ce which is bce to be pre-history
because
according to them there was no history
before the supposed birth of jesus
christ
so this is a very eurocentric worldview
and we have adopted and
internalized these things and today even
i have to talk about bce and c because
if i don't use these terms
my audience will not know what i am
talking about so
india had its own calendrical system
we have the shaka era we had the vikram
samwat era
which are still used to some extent and
we also had the great saptarshi calendar
which
started sometime around 6000 something
bce
so our history is very much older but we
have abandoned it
in modern post-independence
india okay let me take one more question
abhinav asks what led to nehru giving
refuge to the tibetans and the dalai
lama
as a socialist anglophile and chinese
appeaser what led
to this move well mr nehru was
he was a confused person he had no
actual uh
he wanted to appear to be a statesman
he was a self-styled global leader one
of the great
colossal towering figures in the world
and he was the he considered himself to
be a leader of the non-aligned movement
and he always spoke about ethics and
morality
and he used to moralize on global
platforms and all that and it is in
light of this
that he offered refuge to the tibetans
and to the dalai lama
even though he was instrumental in
supplying
rice and other food items to the
invading chinese soldiers in tibet
without mr nehru's assistance the
chinese would not even have been able to
conquer tibet
so this is the dichotomy that you see in
mr nero who is a confused person
the great sri nehru we have to address
him with great respect but he was very
confused
he helped the chinese occupied tibet
without his help it would not have
happened
and then he offered refuge to the
tibetans and to the dalai lama in india
and this was then taken by the chinese
as
a great pretext to go to war with india
as well
so that is the thing about mr nero i
think i should do a separate
separate episode about mr himself
because he has contributed a great deal
to our country
anyhow that brings us to an end to this
episode
thank you very much my friends for all
your questions for participating for
your viewership i
appreciate it very much thank you so
much and i will see you
in the next episode thank you take care
have a good day have a good night
bye